原视频名：Why SpaceX Wants To Make Landing Super Heavy MORE Difficult.
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/lEAyjtIIccY
原视频发布日期：20210102
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And happy 2021 to everybody that is joining me well since 2020.
祝大家2021年快乐 当然主要是那些2020年就关注我的人
So this is an update on some interesting stuff that came out about SpaceX's Super Heavy/Starship.
那么 这个视频是关于SpaceX的Super Heavy/Starship的一些有趣的更新
So to make a disambiguation, right.
那么需要澄清的是
Starship is the thing that's already flown
Starship是已经飞过的
and has been test flown and crashed spectacularly in which everyone cheered on
而且在大家的欢呼声中壮丽地坠毁了
because it was an achievement in many ways even although it failed to stick the landing.
因为其虽未能坚持到着陆 但在很多方面都获得了成就
Now Super Heavy is the booster that is supposed to carry this.
那么 超重助推器是用来运载Starship的火箭
So this is the lower stage.
也就是说它是下面级
I have built a sort of Kerbal version
我差不多建造了一个坎巴拉的版本
and I'm going to admit right away the proportions on this are not correct
而我得马上承认这上面的比例是不对的
because I'm just trying to build something that flies so I can demonstrate some critical features.
因为我只是想做一些会飞的东西 这样我就可以展示一些关键的功能了
Everybody else they use blender and other stuff.
其他的人都在用blender之类的东西
They have mad skills.
他们的技术都很厉害
I wasted all that time learning science.
而我把所有的时间都浪费在学习科学上了
So I'm playing video games instead.
所以我(只能)改玩电子游戏了
How does that work?
那这是怎么做的呢？
So Super Heavy is going to mass about 3 500 tons.
那么超重助推器的质量大概会是3500吨
It's going to mass more than the Saturn V.
它的质量比土星五号还大
It's going to have something like 28 Raptor engines
它会有28台猛禽发动机
and it will carry the Starship second stage up to an altitude
它将携带Starship二级达到这样的高度
where it can then kick in with all six of its Raptor engines, 3 vacuum, 3 sea level
也就是能够同时点火3台真空发动机 3台海平面发动机
and carry that into orbit.
并将Starship送入轨道
And then of course it will do the now familiar SpaceX trick of turning around
当然 它还会做现在大家熟悉的SpaceX把戏 就是掉头
and using its rockets to land back at the base.
并使用其火箭降落回发射场
But there's something that came up in the last few days.
但在过去几天 发生了件事
A comment by Elon that makes a radical change to how this works.
马一龙的一句话 让这个工作方式发生了根本性的变化
So Falcon 9 as you've probably seen many times it can land on the drone ship.
那么猎鹰9号你可能已经看过很多次了 它可以在无人船上降落
It can land on the barge.
也就是在驳船上降落
It has these big landing legs that fold out
还有这些大的可展开的着陆腿
and they have shock absorbers and crushed cores to absorb the force.
而它们有减震器和粉碎芯来吸收作用力
These big legs they're some of the largest pieces of carbon fiber composites that are made on a regular basis.
这些着陆腿基本上算是最大的量产碳纤维部件之一
They're really massive if you look next at people.
如果有人在旁边作对比 就会发现真的很庞大
The grid fins are titanium, the largest single forged pieces of titanium according to Elon Musk.
据马一龙说 栅格翼是最大的单件锻造钛
Starship, the grid fins will be way bigger.
而Starship的栅格翼将更大
They will be welded stainless steel
它们的栅格翼会是焊接不锈钢
and I've seen images of these that show them.
而我见过这些栅格翼的图片
They're like nine meters long.
差不多有九米长
Some people talk about grid fins and say they look a bit like fly swatters.
有些人说栅格翼看起来有点像苍蝇拍
Well these are big enough that you can swat light aircraft out of the sky.
好吧 这些栅格翼大到可以把轻型飞机直接拍下来的程度
Seriously there's a reason we have range safety.
严肃地说 飞行区域安全是有原因的
So Elon's big announcement is that instead of having big landing lags for Super Heavy
那么马一龙的重大声明是 超重助推器不会有大的着陆腿
they would really like to use the grid fins as landing devices.
而他们真的很想使用栅格翼作为着陆装置
And that seems a little crazy because they're obviously all the way up there.
这似乎有点疯狂 因为它们显然一直处在比较高的位置
but they are structurally sound.
但它们的结构是可靠的
What they want to do is instead of having landing legs that go down in the ground,
他们想做的是替代着陆腿 来落到地面上
they will have a device near the launch pad which catches the grid fins.
在发射台附近 他们会设置一种装置来抓住栅格翼
And keeps the bottom of the rocket off the ground which helps in many ways.
让火箭的底部离开地面
I mean there's so many ways this helps.
在很多方面都有利
The main reason why you wouldn't do it is
而不这么做的主要原因是
because it's staggeringly difficult to get this level of landing precision.
要达到这样的着陆精度是非常困难的
In fact here's me totally faking it in Kerbal Space Program.
事实上 这是我在坎巴拉太空计划中完全伪造出来的
You know I did that? I played the video in reverse.
你知道我是怎么做的吗？我把视频倒放了
But assuming you can get that level of precision,
但假设你能达到这种程度的精度
the advantages are that you've shifted a lot of weight off of your launch vehicle and onto the launch stand.
好处是 你已经把很多重量从运载火箭转移到了发射架上
You now no longer need big shock absorbers on the vehicle.
现在你不再需要在火箭上安装大的减震器
Those can be on the stand and they can have a much larger travel range.
这些都可以在支架上 同时行程范围更大
You can also design your capture rig so that the engines remain as far off the ground as possible
你也可以这样设计捕获装置 使发动机尽可能地远离地面
and include a water sound suppression system.
同时包含一个喷水降噪系统
Because of course during landing and retro propulsion
当然是因为在降落和反推过程中
you've got a lot of thermal energy impacting on the back of the rocket
会有大量的热能冲击火箭的底部
but the real point where the engines get damaged is when they are brought to within meters off the ground
而关键的是 发动机在距离地面几米的时候会被损坏
and the shock waves from that thrust are reflecting back off into the engine bay.
而推力产生的冲击波又反射到了发动机舱里
I mean we saw an engine get damaged on serial number eight when they were doing a static fire test.
我是指 在SN8静态点火测试时 上面有一台发动机(因此)损坏了
b23.tv/av800367858
Remember when we were concerned that the oxygen header tank might explode.
还记得当时我们在担心氧气头部储罐是否会爆炸
And another reason cited by Elon is post vehicle processing and return to the launch site
而马一龙提到的另一个原因是 航天器的后续处理以及返回发射场的问题
which should be really fast if you're pretty much landing on the launch site.
如果你几乎是在发射场上降落的话 进行这些操作就会非常迅速
It's also interesting to note that the official SpaceX animation doesn't show this.
同样有趣的是 SpaceX的官方动画并没有展示出这部分是怎么做的
They carefully avoid showing this so I'm wondering if that was on the books back then.
他们小心翼翼地避免展示这一点 所以我在想是不是那时这计划还停留在纸面上(?)
You do get to see the large grid fins which are actually really good designs
你确实可以看到大栅格翼 这实际上是非常好的设计
if you're wanting to build a system that captures with imperfect alignment.
如果你想在不完美对准的情况下建立一个捕获的系统
If you think about it you've got a lot of holes in there
仔细想想 就会发现这上面有很多洞
and you just need a bunch of posts that will slip up between the grid fins and lock the thing in place.
而只需要一堆柱子 让其滑到栅格翼之间 并锁定
This is very similar to what the Soviet Union planned for their docking in lunar orbit.
这和苏联计划在月球轨道上的对接非常相似
But the obvious downside is that if something goes wrong during the landing
但缺点很明显 如果在着陆过程中出了问题
you're not just out a launch vehicle and a bit of concrete.
你不只是丢了枚火箭和一点儿混凝土
You have to rebuild your entire launch stands.
你还得重建你的整个发射台
so for safety reasons for operational reasons you probably have to build multiple launch stands.
所以为了安全的运营 你可能要建造多个发射架
Just to make sure that you can keep up your cadence.
只是为了确保你能跟上发射的节奏
Remember one of the critical things about Starship is the whole orbital refueling capability.
要记得 Starship关键是要有完整的在轨补加能力
And that means you need to be able to reliably launch like half a dozen launch vehicles within a day or so
这意味着你要能在一天或几天之内可靠地发射好几发运载火箭
to make sure that you can refuel your vehicle quickly enough
以确保能迅速地为的航天器补加推进剂
to head off on its grand voyage to the moon or wherever it wants to go.
以完成前往月球或任何想去的地方的伟大旅程
Now we've all become familiar with the Falcon 9 landings and they do look amazingly precise
现在 我们已经熟悉了猎鹰9号的着陆过程 而且它们看起来确实非常精确
but when the barges come back to port it's clear that they're all over the barges.
但是当驳船回到港口的时候 很明显 回收的一级姿态横七竖八的
So you might wonder can they really get this level of precision
那么你可能会想 他们真的能达到这样的精度吗？
and I just say I don't know.
我只能说我不知道
It's obviously a big call.
这显然是一个很大的决定
But the Super Heavy will have one big advantage over the Falcon 9.
但超重助推器比猎鹰9号有一个很大的优势
It will be able to hover.
它将能够悬停
The Falcon 9 has too much thrust and they cannot perform a hover.
猎鹰9号的推力太大而无法进行悬停
So it has to perform a continuous deceleration and end up exactly on the landing pad.
所以它必须要进行连续的减速 最后准确的落在着陆台上
Whereas Super Heavy will have much more time to adjust its course
而超重助推器将有更多的时间来调整它的弹道
and make sure that it is able to put itself in position.
并确保自己处在正确的位置
So I think that it's probably possible
所以我认为 这是很有可能的
but I still say it will be very impressive when they actually do it.
但我还是要说 如果他们真的做到了 那将会非常令人印象深刻
Having special equipment to capture a rocket and slow it down to safe velocity is not a new idea.
拥有特殊的设备来捕获火箭并将其减速到安全速度并不是一个新的想法
This patent was granted in the 1950s
这项专利在20世纪50年代就已经出现了
and this is why you should ignore all those patents from the US navy labs
这就是你应该忽略那些来自美国海军实验室的专利的原因
which talk about anti-gravity and things like that
那些专利都在讨论反重力之类的东西
because you don't actually need to demonstrate something works to patent it.
因为你实际上不需要验证什么东西的工作原理就可以来申请专利
I mean there are a lot of people out there that
我是指 有很多人
point out that all of Elon Musk's big innovations are actually old ideas from other people
指出 马一龙的所有重大创新其实都是别人的老点子
and there's a certain amount of truth to it.
那么这是有一定的道理
But in most cases these previous ideas were never convincing enough to actually get funded
但在大多数情况下 之前的这些想法总是没有足够的说服力来真正获得资金的支持
or were considered too dangerous too radical too likely to fail.
或被认为太危险 太激进 太可能失败了
And when you're throwing your own money around I guess
而当你把自己的钱投出去的时候 我觉得
you can afford to bet big on ideas which other people have thrown away as too risky.
你有能力在别人因风险太大而抛弃的想法上 大大地下注
And the gains on a landing like this are definitely up there.
而类似于这样的着陆方法肯定是有收益的
But you have to get your navigation down 100%
但导航得完全可靠
or you have to put in a lot of launch sites
或者必须建造大量的发射场
to make sure you can deal with launch site and landing site attrition.
以确保你能处理好发射场和着陆场的损耗
There is another comment that was telling about how they're going to use helium pressure
还有一个评论是说他们将如何使用氦气来加压
and if you remember they'd specifically said they were not going to need to use helium pressure
如果你还记得的话 他们特别说过是不需要使用氦气来加压的
and they didn't want to use it.
而且他们也不想使用它
But it looks like they're still having problems with their autogenous pressurization
但现在看来他们的自生加压还是有问题的
and the fact that they had low pressure in the fuel header tank
而头部储罐的过低压力
which caused the serial number eight failed landing
导致SN8着陆失败
is probably a good indication that they're trying to do something whatever it takes
这可能意味着 他们正在不惜一切代价
just to get this thing flying and landing.
只是为了让这个东西(成功)飞行并降落
Given how fast they moved on from the SN8 crash to SN9,
鉴于他们从SN8的坠毁到SN9(测试)的行动速度很快
I speculated the problem was something that they really understood well
我推测 他们是真的很了解这个问题
and something they could fix without the vehicle being in the high bay.
而且他们可以在Starship不进高湾厂房的情况下进行修复
And I actually thought it was something as simple as perhaps sequencing their valves incorrectly
而实话说 我以前还以为只是简单的阀门启动顺序不对而已
and then causing part of the system to either be over pressured or under pressure and fail.
然后导致部分系统压力过大或过小而失效
But it's entirely possible that maybe they had the helium stuff set up on hand
但也完全有可能是很容易安装氦气加压的设备
or that it's easy enough to kind of plumb that into their existing pressurance system.
或者说很容易就能把它接入到现有的加压系统中去
Either way we are expecting SpaceX to continue into the new year with their high-risk-high-reward strategy
不管是哪种方式 我们预计SpaceX新的一年将继续他们的高风险高回报的战略
which will lead to quite a few spectacular moments like the end of SN8.
这将导致相当多的壮观时刻 类似SN8的坠毁
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]